Guide to Maria Irene Fornés Papers MSS 413
Fales Library and Special Collections
Maria Irene Fornés Papers
Bulk, 1980-1999
1909-2004
MSS 413
Fales Library and Special Collections
18.5 linear feet in 38 document boxes, 1 oversize folder, and 14 computer files.
Maria Irene Fornés (b. 1930) is a Cuban-American avant-garde dramatist, director, and teacher of playwriting. Her work, most particularly associated with both the Off-Broadway and Off-Off Broadway movements of the 1960s and New York City's "downtown scene" of the 1980s, has had a major influence on several generations of American playwrights. Winner of 9 Obies, as well as numerous additional awards and honors, Fornés wrote over 50 works for the stage between 1961 and 2001. Her best-known pieces are Fefu and Her Friends (1977), The Danube (1982), Mud (1983), and Promenade (1965), a musical play. The papers document more than half of Fornés’ entire oevre, in original and annotated playscripts, libretti, and adapted works dating from 1965 through 2001; they also document Fornés’ writing process through notes, scenarios, character sketches, and other writings. The remainder of the papers consists of business and professional documents, personal correspondence, family papers, and subject files. The entire collection spans 1912 through 2004, but most of its materials date from the 1980s and 1990s.
Fornes, Maria Irene
INTAR (Theatrical company: New York, N.Y.).
Scope and Content
The papers span 1912 to 2004, with the bulk from the 1980s and 1990s, and were created during the course of Irene Fornés’ playwriting and directing, teaching, administrative and organizational activities and personal relationships. They include play scripts in both paper and electronic form, production notes, set designs and drawings, correspondence, family papers, newspaper clippings, play and book reviews, itineraries, travel ephemera, grant proposals, contracts, play programs, workshop exercises, and student work, as well as notes, play ideas, scenarios, scripted dialog and monologues, and other writings in process. The collection illustrates writing and research processes of a playwright, teaching playwriting, and some aspects of the business and financial sides of the life of a working artist; it also includes personal correspondence and family documents used as source materials for dramatic pieces, and internal and administrative documents of an ethnic theater arts organization.
Bibliography
The following materials were drawn upon for the Biographical Note in this finding aid.
Als, Hilton. “The Plays Of Maria Irene Fornés At INTAR.” The New Yorker (March 22 2010). Retrieved from http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/notebook/2010/03/22 on June 23, 2015.
Black, Rosie. “Enter the Night: Lush Poetry.” The Stranger, Seattle, Washington (April 26-May 2, 1993).
Cummings, Scott T. Maria Irene Fornés. London and New York: Routledge, 2013.
Downey, Roger. “Theater of the Superb.” Seattle Weekly, Seattle, Washington (April 28, 1993).
Harrington, Stephanie. “Irene Fornés, Playwright: Alice and the Red Queen.” Village Voice, New York, New York (April 21, 1966), pp.33-34.
Kelly, Kevin. “A Dramatic and Visual Knockout from Trinity Rep.” The Boston Globe, Boston, Massachusetts (January 13, 1990).
Kozinn, Allan. "Theater World Friends Bring Ailing Playwright Closer to Home." The New York Times. Retrieved from http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/06/?_php=true&_type=blogs&_r on July 1, 2015.
Obejas, Achy. “María Irene Fornés returns to NYC but custody struggle continues.” Achy Objejas. WBEZ91.5 (Chicago Public Radio), 2 February 2013. Web. June 23, 2015.
Wetzsteon, Ross. “A Different Light: The First Annual Dionysia Festival.” Village Voice, New York, New York (August 11, 1992).
Appraisal note
Duplicate clippings and documents from the same folders as originals have been discarded. A video recording of D.W. Griffiths' Broken Blossoms was removed from the files for Enter the Night in Series 1 and deaccessioned. Published books found within research files in Series I were also removed for deaccession.
Separated Materials
No materials have been separated from this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections. Advance notice is required for the use of electronic records.
Biographical/Historical note
Maria Irene Fornés is a Cuban-American avant-garde dramatist, director, and teacher of playwriting. Her work, most particularly associated with both the Off-Broadway and Off-Off Broadway movements of the 1960s and the “downtown scene” of New York City in the 1980s, has had a major influence on several generations of American playwrights. Winner of 9 Obies, as well as numerous additional awards and honors, Fornés wrote over 50 works for the stage between 1961 and 2001. Subjects of her work have included women’s lives, lesbian love, Cuban culture, poverty, and emigration; and themes have featured social, political, and interpersonal power relationships.
Fornés was born on May 14, 1930, in Havana, Cuba, the youngest of six children of Carlos Luis and Carmen Hismenia (Collado) Fornés. Her father, a self-taught intellectual, worked at modest white-collar government jobs and her mother had been a teacher before marriage. The family was poor, but cultured. Fornés, with less than four years of formal schooling, was mostly educated at home.
At age 15, Irene (as she began to call herself) emigrated to the United States with her mother and a sister. There she worked at a number of routine jobs to support herself, including in a ribbon factory. In 1947 Fornés took a folk-dancing class at New York City’s New School through which she was introduced to Greenwich Village’s Bohemian arts and culture scene. She soon moved to Greenwich Village, where she continued to live for the next forty years. During the 1950s she studied painting with abstract impressionist Hans Hoffman; from 1954 through 1957 she was an expatriate, traveling in Europe and living in Paris with American writer Harriet Sohmers Zwerling. In Paris she met Susan Sontag and they became lovers. After her return to the United States the two lived together for several years and Fornés worked as a textile designer.
According to Fornés’ account, it was through her relationship with Sontag that she began to write plays—accidentally, she claimed, in an attempt to help Sontag begin her own writing by demonstrating how easy it was to start. Fornés’ first play, written in Spanish, La Viuda ( The Widow), was written in 1961, followed by There, You Died! (renamed Tango Palace)—her first play in English—in 1963, which was immediately accepted and staged by a San Francisco theater company. Fornés, who had heretofore never received any theatrical or dramatic training, joined the Playwrights Unit of the Actors Studio and took a Method acting course. The years 1965 and 1966 saw the writing and production of Fornés’ only commercial success, Promenade, a play with music written by Al Carmines, a colleague at the Judson Poets Theater; and The Office, her only foray into Broadway theater, which closed after previews. After this early turn towards mainstream theater, Fornés’ plays were performed exclusively Off-Broadway (and its equivalent venues in other parts of the country as well as in Europe) or in college or university productions. She began to direct most of her own works and directed, adapted, and translated other playwrights’ work as well; she also collaborated with composers to create operas. Perhaps her best-known plays, produced in the 1970s and 1980s, are Fefu and Her Friends (1977), The Danube (1983), and Mud (1983). She was honored with awards and obtained artist residencies, grants, and commissioned works. Nearly two dozen of her plays were published, although a significant number of them were performed not more than once or twice or were never staged beyond a workshop performance.
As recognition of Fornés’ plays spread, it brought invitations to visit other countries. Her extensive travels to present or discuss her work included trips to Mexico, India, Japan, Germany, North Africa, the Middle East and the Soviet Union. Irene Fornés’ work as a teacher of playwriting and mentor to emerging playwrights has been recognized and praised as much, if not more, than her plays. The many workshops, classes, and lectures she presented, including her long association with the Hispanic American theater organization INTAR (International Arts Relations, Inc.) exercised a considerable influence on emerging playwrights, in particular a generation of young Latino playwrights. Fornés’ organizational work was important as well. In addition to her service on the council of the Dramatists’ Guild of America, in 1973 she co-founded New York Theatre Strategy, a writer-centered cooperative theater production company and spent so much time acting variously as its producer, fundraiser, costumer, publicist and administrator that for several years she laid aside her own writing and directing.
In 2001 illness forced Irene Fornés to retire. Her last completed play (first produced in 2000) was Letters from Cuba; her last working play was 27 Rue de Fleurus, a piece about the life of Gertrude Stein.
Custodial History
Circa 2006 the papers were gathered and moved from Irene Fornés' apartment to the offices of Eduardo Machado at New York University; they were then transferred to the offices of PAJ--A Journal of Performance and Art in approximately 2008. In October 2014, the papers were donated by Bonnie Marranca, editor of PAJ, on behalf of the journal.
Related Archival Materials note
Judson Memorial Church Archive (MSS 094)
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in eight series, the first of which has been further arranged into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement is as follows:
Series I: Play Scripts and Production Records
Subseries 1: Plays by Fornés
Subseries 2: Plays by Others Directed by Fornés
Series II: Notes, Scenarios, and Writings in Process
Series III: Business and Finance Files
Series IV: INTAR (International Arts Relations, Inc.) Records
Series V: Family Papers
Series VI: Personal Correspondence
Series VII: Teaching Materials and Students’ Work
Series VIII: Subject/Research Files
Folders are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title with the exception of Series IV, which is arranged in chronological order.
Fornes, Maria Irene; INTAR (Theatrical company: New York, N.Y.).; Marranca, Bonnie; PAJ--A Journal of Performance and Art.; Cuban American women; Cuban Americans |z Ethnic identity; Ethnic arts.; Experimental theater |z New York (State) |z New York.; Hispanic American theater |z New York (State) |z New York.; Manuscripts for publication.; Off Off-Broadway theater.; Playbills.; Playwriting.; Scripts (documents); Theater programs.; Theater |x History |y 20th century.; Theater |x Production and direction.; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century.
- Series I: Play Scripts and Production Records, 1965-2003; 8.5 linear feet in 16.5 document boxes and 13 computer files.
  Arrangement
  This series was divided into two subseries to distinguish between Fornés' work as a writer and director of her own plays and her work directing and translating plays of other authors. Folders in both subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by play title. For each title, folders are arranged by genre or document type. In cases in which plays are known by different titles, the best-known title is listed first, followed by the alternate title. Some folders may contain material for multiple titles.
  Scope and Content
  This series includes original and revised scripts in both paper and electronic format for a little over half of Irene Fornés’ work, including some of her earliest plays and her last working play, Rue de Fleurus (concerning Gertrude Stein). It also includes a script for Minuski, a previously-unknown work, and La Plaza Chica, Fornés' translation and adaptation of her play Abingdon Square into Spanish. In addition, there are scores for some of her plays with songs; a libretto for an opera; and scripts and staging notes for Fornés’ directing, translating, and adapting of other writers’ plays or stories (such as Henrik Ibsen's Hedda Gabler and Anton Chekhov's Uncle Vanya and Drowning). There are numerous drafts or versions of Fornes’ scripts written, edited, or adapted for different productions of a play, or revised after the completion of a run of a particular production. Many of the scripts are not complete, and most of them have Fornés’ handwritten--often extensive--annotations and revisions. Production records for various stagings of her own plays and productions she directed of others’ works include memos, notes, set designs, cast lists, and calls for auditions.
  - Subseries A: Plays by Fornés, 1961-2001
    - Abingdon Square and La Plaza Chica--Scripts, 1986-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-11, Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Abingdon Square and La Plaza Chica--Scripts, 1992-1993; FA_MSS_413_ER_1; 345.3 kilobytes in 8 computer files. (Item ER 1)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      345.3 Kilobytes (8 computer files).
    - Abingdon Square--Poster and Reviews, 1992, undated (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
    - The Audition--Scripts and Notes, 1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Aurora--Scripts, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Balseros (aka Manual for a Desperate Crossing)--Partial Script, Production Materials, Oral History Interview Transcripts, circa 1995-1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
    - Cap-A-Pie--Script, Budget, Set Designs, Notes, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
    - The Conduct of Life (No Time)--Production Photographs and Negatives, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - The Conduct of Life (No Time)--Script--French Translations and Program, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1, Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Danube--Scripts (including German translation) and Script Fragments, 1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    - A Diary of Evelyn Brown--Production Photograph, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Dr. Kheal--Script--French Translation, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Dr. Kheal, Molly's Dream, Tango Palace, The Successful Life of 3--Photocopies of Published Scripts (With Corrections), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Drowning--Script--Photocopy of Published Version, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Enter the Night (aka Dreams)--Scripts and Production Materials, 1993-1999, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
    - Eyes on the Harem--Partial Script and Research Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Fefu and Her Friends--Posters, undated (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
    - Fefu and Her Friends--Production Materials and Scripts, 1987-1999, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-20)
      Various versions for different productions; one is a Spanish translation.
    - Fefu and Her Friends--Scripts, 1998; FA_MSS_413_ER_2; 184.7 kilobytes in 3 computer files. (Item ER 2)
      184.7 Kilobytes (3 computer files).
    - Girls Can't Kiss--Screenplays, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 21-23, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Golonda [possibly aka The Curse of Langdon House]--Script, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Cuba--Scripts, 2000, undated (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Lolita in the Garden--Program and Copies of Production Photographs, circa 1977 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Lovers and Keepers--Photocopy of Published Script, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Minushki--Script and Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Mud--Press Packet and Production Photographs, 1983, 1999, undated (Box 6, Folder 10-12)
    - Mud, The Danube, The Conduct of Life, Sarita--Photocopies of Published Scripts, undated (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    - Oscar and Bertha--Floor Plan and Set Design Elevations, 1992 (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
    - Oscar and Bertha (aka Brother and Sister)--Scripts, 1987-1992, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-11, Box 6, Folder 15-17)
    - Oscar and Bertha--Script, 1993; FA_MSS_413_ER_3; 61.0 kilobytes in 1 computer file. (Item ER 3)
      61 Kilobytes (1 computer file).
    - The Office--Scripts, circa 1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
    - Promenade--Script--Published Versions (Some with Handwritten Revisions), undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Promenade--Photograph, circa 1960s (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
    - The Red Burning Light Or: Mission XQ3--Script--Photocopies of Published Version, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Sarita--Script--Partial Drafts and Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - The Successful Life of 3--Production Photographs, circa 1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Summer in Gossensass (Ibsen and the Actress)--Production Materials, 1994-1995, undated (Box 8, Folder 5-8)
    - The Summer in Gossensass--Scripts, 1996-1998, undated (Box 11, Folder 1, Box 10, Folder 1-17, Box 9, Folder 1-20, Box 8, Folder 9-28)
    - Terra Incognita--Librettos and Scores, 1992-1997 (Box 13, Folder 1, Box 12, Folder 1-8)
    - Terra Incognita--Production and Research Materials, 1994-1997 (Box 11, Folder 6-14)
    - Terra Incognita--Script, 1992; FA_MSS_413_ER_4; 31.81 kilobytes in 1 computer file. (Item ER 4)
      31.81 Kilobytes (1 computer file).
    - Terra Incognita--Scripts, 1996-1997, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
    - Twins--Scripts, Research Notes and Materials, Drawings, Audition Notes, Contract, 1992-1993 (Box 13, Folder 5-8)
    - A Vietnamese Wedding--Script--Photocopies of Published Version, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - A Visit--Parts of Script Draft or Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - What of the Night (The Mothers, early version of Nadine)--Production Notes from Padua Hills Playwrights Workshop, circa 1986 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - What of the Night--Scripts, 1988-1993, undated (Box 15, Folder 1-7, Box 14, Folder 1-15, Box 13, Folder 12-17)
      What of the Night is a quartet of related plays some of whose individual titles changed over time. These component plays were titled variously as: The Mothers, Nadine, Hunger, Springtime, Lust, Charlie.
    - The Widow--Production Photographs, circa 1961 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 27 Rue de Fleurus--Scripts and Research Materials, 2001, undated (Box 15, Folder 9-16, Box 16, Folder 1-16)
    - Unidentified Plays--Production Photographs, Contact Sheets, Negatives, 1987, undated (Box 16, Folder 17-20)
    - Unidentified Play--Photograph, undated (Map-case 2.C, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Play ("Zoila Y Berta in the Malecon 1903")--Script Fragement, undated (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified Play ("Rob and Tom")--Script Fragment, undated (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Subseries B: Plays by Others Directed by Fornés, 1984-1997
    - Hedda Gabler--Script and Production Notes, 1987, undated (Box 16, Folder 23-24)
    - It Is It Is Not (by Manuel Pereiras)--Production Materials, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 25, Box 17, Folder 1)
    - It Is It Is Not (by Manuel Pereiras)--Scripts, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Life is a Dream--Script Fragments, Song, Research, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified Play (Possibly Life Is a Dream)--Set Design and Production Snapshots, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Uncle Vanya--Script, Casting, Production Notes, Research, 1987, undated (Box 17, Folder 3-7)
- Series II: Notes, Scenarios, and Writings in Process, 1980s-1990s, undated; 2.75 linear feet in 4.75 document boxes.
  This series contains diverse writings and drawings on paper recording Fornés’ internal artistic processes and ideas. It includes notes, scenarios, stories and character studies; dialogs, monologues and individual lines; ideas for plays, films and dances; journal and diary entries; fragments of narratives and numerous other types of writings in process; and a small amount of correspondence. Some of the writings are typed, and many are handwritten. Formats range from notebooks to the backs of envelopes and smaller scraps. Almost none of the items are dated, with the exception of a few materials from the 1980s to the 1990s. Most of the materials originally received in labeled folders retain their original folder titles (these are enclosed by quotation marks); the remaining materials have been placed in folders labeled “miscellaneous.”
  - "A.E.", undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "Alice in Wonderland", undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - "Americans--Directors", undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - "Analfabetos", undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - "Annuciation Movie", undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - "Applicant", undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - "Ashlea, Atlanta and Trip", undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - "Assassination", undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - "Baby Lesbian", undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - "Baby MacQueeney", undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - "Being Hip", undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - "Betty", undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - "Biography", undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - "Biography", undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - "Biography Show", undated (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - "Blacklist", undated (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - "The Boy", undated (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - "Brake-Down", undated (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - "Carl", undated (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - "Carreno", undated (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - "Cata Film", undated (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - "The Child of Prague", undated (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - "Children Stories", undated (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - "Crisis", undated (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - "Disregard", undated (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - "Drawings", undated (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - "East Side", undated (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - "Eve's Story", undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "Expo", undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Family Tree/Genealogy, undated (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - "Femin", 1969, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - "Flats", undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "The Flying Nazi", undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - "Here I Am (Dance)", undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "Hong Kong Play", undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - "Hotel Renata", undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - "Houses", undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - "Ibiza", undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - "Idra Story", undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - "Indian Play", undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - "Interview", undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - "Interiew II", undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - "John", undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - "Lady Hester Stanhope", undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - "LBJ", undated (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - "Mama (Notas Y Datos)", undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - "Mary T.", undated (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - "Maureen (Custody)", undated (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - "Meg", undated (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - "Mexican Stories", undated (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - "Monte Cristo", undated (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - "Natale" [Libretto Idea], undated (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - "Necklace", undated (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - "Observatoir", undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - "Nicholas and Alexandra", undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - "Not Typed -- Monologues", undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - "The Old Lady", undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - "Orphans", undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - [Pancho] "Villa", undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "Prince", undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - "Purse", undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - "Rape", undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - "Singles to Be Typed (Scenes)", undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - "Singles Typed Dialogue", undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - "Singles Typed (Not Dialogue)", undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - "Sirio and Belén", undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - "Stamp", undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - "Quotes", undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - "Thoughts", undated (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - "Turin", undated (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - "TW TW TW", undated (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - "Typed Monologue", undated (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - "Vitamin Dispenser", undated (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - "Vulgar People", undated (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - "W & Y", undated (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - "What's Her Name", undated (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - "Words", undated (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - "Writings", undated (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - "Writings in Spanish", undated (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - "Yoruba", undated (Box 20, Folder 23)